<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sutable [sic] comforts for suffering Sion; or, saints interest in God, their chiefest support in times of greatest straits Being a brief discovery of what God is to his people in all ages: which is of great weight and use to his in these trying times. Written by Edward Delamaine, at present under restraint, and a prisoner of hope.</title>
            <author>Delamaine, Edward.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82290</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D867</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R231384</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897285</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897285</idno>
            <idno type="VID">137005</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82290)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 137005)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2480:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sutable [sic] comforts for suffering Sion; or, saints interest in God, their chiefest support in times of greatest straits Being a brief discovery of what God is to his people in all ages: which is of great weight and use to his in these trying times. Written by Edward Delamaine, at present under restraint, and a prisoner of hope.</title>
                  <author>Delamaine, Edward.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Simon Dover, and are to be sold at his house in Christophers Alley, in Martins Le Grand,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:137005:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:137005:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:137005:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:137005:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SUTABLE COMFORTS FOR Suffering Sion; OR, SAINTS INTEREST in GOD, their Chiefeſt SUPPORT in times of greateſt Straits. BEING A Brief DISCOVERY of what GOD is to his People in all Ages: Which is of great Weight and Uſe to His in theſe Trying Times. Written by EDWARD DELAMAINE, at preſent under Reſtraint, and a PRISONER of HOPE.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ISAIAH 40.1, 2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Comfort ye, Comfort ye my People, ſaith your God; Speak comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably to them.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Simon Dover,</hi> and are to be Sold at his Houſe in <hi>Chriſtophers</hi> Alley, in <hi>Martins Le Grand.</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:137005:3"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:137005:3"/>
            <head>SUTABLE COMFORTS FOR Suffering Sion; OR, SAINTS INTEREST in GOD their Chiefeſt Support in times of greateſt Straits.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Ear Brethren, and fellow Companions of the Kingdom of God; This is the day of <hi>Jacobs</hi> Trouble, of <hi>Joſephs</hi> Affliction, of <hi>Zions</hi> Trials, and of the Calamities of the whole <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God; And I find that the People of God in general, are very prone and incident to be Troubled, Caſt down, and Diſquieted; And I find that it is the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of God that his People ſhould be Comforted, Conſolated, and Refreſhed. Therefore in order thereunto, I ſhall offer ſomething, that may anſwer the End and Deſign of God; And the Portion of the Word of God, which I intend to make the Ground of my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, for my own and others Edification, is Recorded in that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Scripture,</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Exod. 3.14, and the laſt part of Verſ. 15.</bibl> 
               <hi>And God ſaid to him, I AM THAT I AM: Say unto them, I AM hath ſent thee: This is my Name for Ever, and my Memorial unto all Generations.</hi>
            </q>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:137005:4"/>
            <p>In order to theſe Words, we may conſider Three things:
<list>
                  <item>1. The Author of theſe Words.</item>
                  <item>2. The Perſon to whom they were Spoken.</item>
                  <item>3. The Occaſion why they were Spoken.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>For the Firſt, The Author of them was the great God of Heaven, the Diſpoſer of all things, the Judge of the whole Earth, the King of kings, and Lord of lords; and therefore conſidering the Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Worthineſs of Him that ſpeaks, we ſhould have the higher eſteem, and give the more diligent heed to what he ſaith.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Perſon to whom theſe Words were ſpoken, and that was <hi>Moſes;</hi> of whom, Three things are mighty Remarkable and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable.</p>
            <p>Firſt, His <hi>Love</hi> to God, in that he forſook all earthly Pleaſures and Delights, and <hi>Choſe rather to ſuffer Affliction with the People of God.</hi> Ah! there be few that take <hi>Moſes</hi> Choice, that chooſe Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs more than Greatneſs, eſteeming Poverty better than Riches, and count Godlineſs more Gain than Wickedneſs, and rather hazard Bonds and Sufferings, than the Violation of their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences with falſe Swearing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That account Raggs with Chriſt, though on a Dunghil, more than Robes without Chriſt, though on a Throne.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Another thing Conſiderable in <hi>Moſes,</hi> was his <hi>Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> which is much commended in him, <hi>Numb.</hi> 12.3. <hi>Now the man Moſes was very Meek above all the men that were in the Earth;</hi> this is a Chriſt-like Spirit, a Mild Gentle Spirit, and to exerciſe ſuch a Spirit to thoſe that are of a Froward, Peeviſh, Proud Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is an excellent Frame; not to return evil for evil, but good for evil; to uſe gentleneſs and mildneſs, for bitterneſs and frowardneſs, is a Carriage that makes Chriſtians look moſt like God: Now <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> was not onely <hi>Meek,</hi> but <hi>very Meek,</hi> and that <hi>above all the men that were upon the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Third thing Remarkable in <hi>Moſes,</hi> was his <hi>Faithfulneſs</hi> for God; See how it is ſpoken to his Praiſe, <hi>Numb.</hi> 12.7. compared with <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.2.</p>
            <p>Touching his <hi>Faithfulneſs</hi> you have Three things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, His being <hi>Faithful to declare to the People the whole mind of God,</hi> as God communicated it to him; Now when God took him up into the Mount, he might have taken liberty to have varied (and no body have queſtioned him) either to have added or to have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:137005:4"/>to what God had left in charge with him, no he doth not, but is <hi>Faithful</hi> to that Truſt delivered to him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, He was <hi>Faithful in doing what God Commanded from him,</hi> in performing Gods Requirements to him, <hi>Exod.</hi> 11.26. and therefore when he tells <hi>Pharaoh, That God would have the Children of Iſrael and all they had, go up with them to Worſhip; Pharaoh</hi> was not willing that their Cattel and Flocks ſhould go: Nay, ſaith <hi>Moſes, We muſt not leave a hoof behind.</hi> So <hi>Faithful</hi> was he for God, that not a tittle of the Service of God, muſt be omited or left undone.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, His <hi>Faithfulneſs</hi> to God appeared, <hi>in that he cloſely follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſerved the Lord even to his laſt day;</hi> He perſevered to the laſt, in a full and faithful following of the Lord, and therefore the Lord writes this praiſe and commendation on <hi>Moſes, He was faithful in all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much ſhall ſuffice as touching the Perſon, to whom the Words were ſpoken. Now I come to the Third thing, the Occaſion; Why the Words of my Text were ſpoken? And in that we ſhall conſider many things very Remarkable.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Moſes</hi> goes to tend upon his Father-in-Law's flock, and in his way, ſees <hi>a Buſh burning,</hi> and turning about, ſaid, <hi>I will ſee this great ſight, why the Buſh burns and is not conſumed.</hi> The Admiration or Wonder in <hi>Moſes,</hi> was not ſo much, that the <hi>Buſh burned,</hi> but that it <hi>burned and was not conſumed;</hi> this was the Wonder then, and it's the Wonder now, yea, and will be in all Ages.</p>
            <p>Give me leave to enlarge a little upon it; This <hi>Buſh</hi> I compare to the <hi>People of God,</hi> and the <hi>Fire,</hi> or <hi>Burning,</hi> to <hi>Afflictions</hi> and <hi>Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> Now it hath been the Marvel in all Ages, that <hi>the Buſh</hi> hath <hi>burned,</hi> and hath <hi>not been conſumed,</hi> that the People of God have been wonderfully carried forth in the midſt of <hi>fiery Tryals,</hi> that they have ſeemed rather to overcome then to be overcome, rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querers then conquered, to be living daily though dying daily; and this hath occaſioned marvel and wonder to the men of the World; Witneſs thoſe three Children in <hi>Daniel,</hi> that were in the <hi>burning Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace,</hi> and yet not <hi>conſumed;</hi> Witneſs thoſe worthy Martyrs of late days, whoſe life and livelineſs in Suffering made their Adverſaries amazed, <hi>that the Buſh burned, and was not conſumed,</hi> when they ſaw their inward man lived and renewed, in the midſt of their dying and bitter deaths. Now if the men of the World would do like dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent <hi>Moſes,</hi> turn aſide and be inquirous to behold this great ſight,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:137005:5"/>to ſearch into the cauſe thereof, they might have their marvel ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, and their wonder removed; <hi>Moſes looked, and belold the Lord was in the midſt of the Buſh.</hi> Hence ſee the cauſe that the People of God have been moſt Eminently preſerved in the Inward-man, and have been born up above and beyond all ſpeakings; in the midſt of all Trials and Sufferings, <hi>God was in the midſt of them; there was, and is, a very gracious Preſence of His, accompanying and aſſiſting of them;</hi> This is the Reaſon, this is the Ground why the <hi>Buſh burns and is not conſumed;</hi> So they in the fire were preſerved, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.24, 25. Now when the Lord out of the Buſh had called to <hi>Moſes,</hi> He ſaid, in the ſeventh <hi>Verſe, I have ſurely ſeen the Affliction of my People in Egypt.</hi> Hence obſerve, <hi>That God takes notice of his Peoples Affliction,</hi> yea, <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial notice; I have ſurely ſeen,</hi> ſaith God. Oh ſuffering Souls! your Conſolations are not ſmall, the Eyes of Heaven are upon you, and your ſufferings; the Eye of Love, and the Eye of Pity, is not onely Preſident over you, but Preſent with you; be you never ſo remote, or obſcure in Suffering, that Eye of Divine Majeſty that runs to and fro throughout the whole Earth, will be firſt on you; <hi>I have,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>ſurely ſeen the Affliction of my People in Egypt.</hi> This is a ſweet Word of God, <hi>My People,</hi> though Afflicted, yet <hi>Mine;</hi> though Oppreſſed and Hated, yet <hi>My People;</hi> It's not their Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, their Miſeries, their Afflictions, that can un-people them, that can break that great cord of Union and Relation, between God and his People; <hi>My People,</hi> though Oppreſſed and Perſecuted, yet <hi>My People;</hi> They are never the more Unlovely in my Eyes, never the more Uncomely, though they are trampled upon as dirt, and made as the off-ſcouring of the World, yet I am not aſhamed to own them, I am not aſhamed to acknowledge them to be <hi>My Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> and therefore I will own them and ſtand by them: They are indeed by their Oppreſſors and Perſecutors (having the rod of the wicked over them, making ſurrows upon them) repreſented very Unlovely, very Uncomely, very Deſpicable and Contemptible; yet nevertheleſs there is not a tittle of my Affection and Love, that I bear to them, abated or diminiſhed, they are <hi>My People,</hi> yea, and <hi>in Egypt.</hi> God doth not onely own his People in the worſt of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, but in the worſt of Places alſo; And therefore he ſaith, <hi>I have ſurely ſeen the Affliction of my People in Egypt; Egypt</hi> was called <hi>The Houſe of Bondage: The Nation of their Oppreſſion: The Land where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they were Slaves and Strangers.</hi> Yet there God owns them, <hi>My
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:137005:5"/>People in Egypt.</hi> It is not Places that makes God at all Diſaffected with his People, though they be thrown into <hi>Newgate,</hi> or elſewhere, the ſhamfulleſt of Goals, by his cruelty, whoſe tender mercies are no better, nor nothing elſe; yet there will God own them; the loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomeſt Dungeons, ſhall not at all keep God from Communion with his People, He will own them though <hi>in Egyt;</hi> and ſaith God, <hi>I know their Sorrows;</hi> Know their Sorrows he doth, and will he not remedie it? Yea ſurely: As if the Lord ſhould ſay, <hi>I am acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with all their Griefs, I am concerned in all their ſufferings:</hi> Oh Chriſtians believe this Truth, <hi>That God ſees all the Afflictions of his People, and knows their Sorrows;</hi> God ſees for this end, and knows for this end, that he might the better communicate ſeaſonable good to his People. And in <hi>Verſe</hi> 10. ſaith God, <hi>Come now therefore, that thou mayeſt bring the Children of Iſrael out of Egypt; Come now,</hi> ſaith God, now is my Time, now is my Opportunity, now is my fit Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to Deliver <hi>My People.</hi> God's Time of working Deliverance for his People, is when they are in the midſt of the greateſt ſtraits and ſufferings. Now the Lord is imploying and ſending <hi>Moſes</hi> with a Meſſage both to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and to his People. <hi>Moſes</hi> very much op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth it, and with the Lord pleads two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. His <hi>own Unworthineſs, Who am I,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that I ſhould go to Pharaoh, that I ſhould be imployed in the ſervice of the great God of Heaven?</hi> The Lord takes off this Objection by Anſwering, <hi>I will be with thee.</hi> The Worthineſs of Gods aſſiſting Preſence, will far ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount and exceed <hi>Moſes</hi> his <hi>Unworthineſs.</hi> One thing here you have worth obſerving, and that is, <hi>That it is not the Meanneſs, Low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Unworthineſs,</hi> (ſimply conſidered) <hi>of poor creatures, that doth exclude or exempt them from Gods ſervice or acceptance;</hi> but ſin will hinder from both.</p>
            <p>A Second thing that <hi>Moſes</hi> pleads againſt his being imployed, is, <hi>Ignorance of Gods Name;</hi> He did not know what Name of God he ſhould carry to his poor ſuffering People; This God anſwers and declares, and ſo I come to my Text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I AM THAT I AM, I AM hath ſent unto them; this is my Name for Ever, and my memorial unto all generations.</hi> In which Words you have Three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A Deſcription or Diſcovery of the Name of God, <hi>I AM THAT I AM,</hi> or <hi>what I ever was.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Perpetuity and Continuance of His Name; <hi>This is my Name for E<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ER.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:137005:6"/>
            <p n="3">3. The uſe of it to his People; <hi>This is my Memorial unto all generations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the Occaſion of the Words, you have this Obſervation.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>That God Proportions out Sutable and Seaſonable Mercies and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, to his Peoples State and Condition.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>You may ſee that this Truth ariſeth naturally from the occaſion of theſe Words, if you conſider that theſe were a People under great Promiſes from the Lord, and alſo from Men under great Sufferings and Oppreſſions; Now to this Afflicted, Oppreſſed People, God ſends this Meſſage, this errand, <hi>I AM THAT I AM:</hi> No Name of God had been ſo Sutable, ſo Seaſonable as this, <hi>I AM the ſame that ever I was.</hi> I ſhall ſhew anon, in due place, how Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, how Sutable this Name of God is, to his Suffering People. If God had ſent to his People his Name <hi>Jah,</hi> or <hi>Jehovah,</hi> it had been ſomething, but it had not been ſo ſeaſonable as <hi>I AM.</hi> God uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtays and delays Deliverance, that it may come moſt Seaſonable and Sutable to his Peoples Conditions; Why muſt they be four hundred years in Affliction? May not two hundred years ſerve? No, at the end of four hundred years, is Gods time for Deliverance, then will his Mercies come moſt Seaſonable. And truly this I am perſwaded, is the very Reaſon why God ſeems to keep away deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance from his People, they are not yet come to the greateſt of ſtraits; the Mercy will not come ſo Seaſonable and Sutable as God would have it. I might be large upon this Point, but I ſhall not at this time, though it is a Truth of great concernment, I ſhall only prove it with an Inſtance or two, with ſome Reaſons, and then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to what remains, which is much upon my heart.</p>
            <p>See <hi>Gen.</hi> 21. from <hi>verſ.</hi> 15. to 21. Poor <hi>Agar</hi> was in great diſtreſs, ſhe and the Babe was like to periſh for want of water, ſhe was in the greateſt of Straits, gave her ſelf and babe over for death, paſt all hope of life; Oh then was Gods time, then was his time to appear, and that with a Sutable and Seaſonabe Mercy to her State and Condition; and pray, What was that? Her condition was ſuch that ſhe had like to have died with <hi>Drought, want of Drink,</hi> for ſhe was in a Remote and barren Wilderneſs, &amp; behold God communicates to her <hi>a Well of Water.</hi> From hence ſee, <hi>That God proportions out Seaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and Sutable Mercies &amp; Comforts to his Peoples Wants &amp; Neceſſities.</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:137005:6"/>From this Remarkable inſtance in <hi>Agar,</hi> you have many conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That Gods People in their greateſt Straits and Wants, make their recourſe by Prayer to God:</hi> this good <hi>Agar</hi> did. <hi>The times of tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ought eſpecially then to be the times of ſupplication. Chriſts Suffering hour was his praying hour. Times of Afflictions puts Saints upon Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons at the Throne of Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Strange and unexpected ways and means of Deliverance hath God for his People.</hi> This is a glorious Truth, but I muſt but name it: Little did poor <hi>Agar</hi> think to find Supplies in the Wilderneſs, no viſible means attainable.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Obſerve, <hi>That there are ſuch Bowels of Mercy and Love in God towards his, that he uſually, yea frequently, not onely grants their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, but gives them more, yea over and above.</hi> Poor <hi>Agar</hi> begs <hi>a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Water</hi> of God to preſerve the life of her and her little babe, and lo, God gives her <hi>a Well of Water.</hi> So <hi>Solomon</hi> asked for <hi>Wiſdome;</hi> God did not onely give him <hi>That,</hi> but <hi>Riches,</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> alſo. I muſt proceed.</p>
            <p>A Second notable Inſtance you have, is, concerning <hi>Sampſon, Judg.</hi> 15.18, 19. He having a very great <hi>thirſt, like to die,</hi> the Lord in a miraculous maner preſerved him, and communicated a Sutable Mercy to him, and gave him <hi>Water out of the Jaw-bone of an Aſs.</hi> One thing here I ſhall mind unto you, that is, Sometimes I have marvelled at the exceeding <hi>Drought</hi> and <hi>Thirſt</hi> that came upon <hi>Sampſon,</hi> immediately after the Deliverance obtained, by the help of the Lord againſt his Enemies. I ſuppoſe that his great <hi>Thirſt</hi> came not by reaſon of his great Fighting; He might be thirſty, but not upon that account unto death, conſidering the Lord helped him; But now for him to be by thirſt, near death, there lies ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it; and therefore I humbly judge, that this thirſt was ſent as a Judgement from the Lord, and that upon two accounts:</p>
            <p n="1">1. His too much Vaunting, Applauding and Praiſing of himſelf for this Victory; See his high proud Words, <hi>With the Jaw of an Aſs have I ſlain a thouſand men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Not returning the Praiſe and Honour to whom it was due, and therefore the Lord might be angry &amp; diſpleaſed with him, &amp; to ſhew him his own weakneſs, frailty and infirmity, that he might not glory in himſelf, but to ſee that without the Lords aſſiſtance, he was but a dead man, &amp; therefore I conceive this thirſt came: And then betook
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:137005:7"/>himſelf to prayer; and though after mercy received, he was unmind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of his duty, yet now his great wants and ſtraits make him mind his duty, and help; and when <hi>Sampſon</hi> had taſted of Gods anger, then you ſhall have him acknowledge God having a hand in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance, but not before.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe the Prophet, having fled into the Wilderneſs, being driven to great wants, the Lord adminiſtred food to him by Ravens; and ſo the Lord communicated Sutable Comforts to his Servant. I might name many more, but I would haſten, and briefly now give you the Reaſons of it. I ſhall at preſent name but two; Why God proportions out <hi>Sutable Mercies to his Peoples Conditions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Firſt is, <hi>To enlarge their Experiences of Him.</hi> Not a Sutable Mercy or Comfort comes to us from God, but it is to ſtock us with Experience; for Experience of God's goodneſs is of great uſe to a dependance on God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It is <hi>To heighten our Praiſes to Him,</hi> that we may much be carried forth in new Songs of Praiſes to the Lord. A word of Uſe to this, and ſo proceed and come to the thing I aim at.</p>
            <p>Seeing God doth proportion out <hi>Sutable Comforts to his Peoples Conditions;</hi> then be Exhorted, <hi>To walk Sutable to ſuch a God as this is, be perſwaded to walk anſwerable to a God of ſuch Sutable Comforts, and ſeaſonable Mercies.</hi> Oh the Sutable Comforts that his poor Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants have enjoyed in their Bonds and Sufferings! that when all the World ſhall frown, then to have the God of Heaven ſmile; that when the World ſtrips us of all outward Injoyments, then to have them made up with inward and ſpecial Injoyments; when the men of the World put a bitter cup into our hands, then for our Father to ſweeten it for us; when we hear the worſt news from Earth, we can then have the beſt news from Heaven: Oh this is <hi>Seaſonable and Sutable Comfort:</hi> It's true we want our Liberties, but yet we have the bleſſed Liberty of the Sons of God: It's true we are in Bonds, under Reſtraint, Oh but yet our ſouls are not in bonds, our Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences are not captivated to ſins and luſts: it's true we are in the hands of cruel and unreaſonable men, but yet we are in the hands of a faithful Creator. Fellow-ſufferers, conſider it and believe it, you that experience Gods goodneſs, in <hi>Sutable Comforts</hi> to you, know, that he expects that it ſhould work rare effects in you, and produce eminent and ſutable walkings towards him. Thus much for the firſt thing, being occaſional from the Words; I ſhall now come to the chief thing I aime at.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:137005:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>I AM THAT I AM, this is my Name for Ever, and my Memorial unto all Generations.</hi> The Doctrine, Concluſion, or wholſome Truth, which ariſes from theſe Words, is this;</p>
            <q>
               <hi>That the great and ſerious Conſideration of Gods Name, I AM, being the ſame to his People in all ages, is of mighty uſe and benefit to Comfort and Conſolate the hearts and ſpirits of his People, in the midſt of all their Troubles and Sufferings.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>This is a great and weighty Truth, and there lieth much ſap and marrow in it, and therefore I do earneſtly deſire that it may dwell in the hearts of all the Suffering ſons of <hi>Sion</hi> this day; and this Truth I judge ariſeth naturally from the Words; for in the Doctrine you may obſerve theſe ſeveral Branches.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>That Gods Name is, I AM.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>That it is ſo for EVER to his People.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>That the ſerious conſideration thereof, is of uſe to Comfort and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate the People of God in their Sufferings.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Now conſider well the Text, and you ſhall find this Truth couch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in it; And conſider the Perſons to whom it was communicated, being the People of the Lord under great Sufferings and Troubles, and you may plainly perceive, that the great aime, and deſigne of God here is, that his People through a ſerious Conſideration of his Name, <hi>I AM THAT I AM,</hi> ſhould be much conſolated and refreſhed, in the midſt of their Troubles and Sufferings.</p>
            <list>
               <head>In the managing of this weighty Truth, I ſhall lay down Four Things.</head>
               <item>I. <hi>Prove it to you, and ſhew you what is Gods Name, and how it endures for Ever.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. <hi>Declare how, and wherein Gods Name, I AM, is the ſame to his People in all ages; and ſhew you that this Truth is of mighty uſe and benefit to bear up their hearts in Suffering.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>III. <hi>Give you the Reaſons of this Truth,</hi> which are very conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, <hi>Why the Lords Name, I AM THAT I AM, is his Name for EVER, and continued to his People to all Generations.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>IV. <hi>Give you the wholſome and ſeaſonable Uſes and Concluſions of this Subject.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>What Gods Name is, and the Duration of it.</hi> This Name of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:137005:8"/>God, <hi>I AM THAT I AM,</hi> is wrapt and bound up in His moſt glorious Attributes; See that notable Text in <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.5, 6. <hi>And proclaimed the Name of the Lord;</hi> Now what was the Name of the Lord? See, and you ſhall find it declared, and held forth in His Attributes, <hi>The Lord, the Lord God, Long-ſuffering, Merciful and Gracious;</hi> Here is the Mercy of God, <hi>keeping Mercy for thouſands, for giving iniquity, tranſgreſſion and ſin;</hi> Here is the Faithfulneſs of God, <hi>and by no means clearing the guilty;</hi> Here is the Juſtice of God. Now that the Name of God endures, ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.26, 27. <hi>They ſhall periſh, but thou ſhalt endure; thou art the ſame, and thy years ſhall have no end.</hi> Here you ſee that this God, who hath declared himſelf <hi>I AM,</hi> is of continuance, he endures, he is the ſame and changes not. Oh it's a bleſſed thing to conſider, that God is now the ſame that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he was, His Name is <hi>I AM,</hi> and <hi>this is his Name for Ever,</hi> Pſal. 72.17. <hi>His Name ſhall endure for Ever, His Name ſhall be continued as long as the Sun, and Men ſhall be bleſſed in him.</hi> Oh this Name of God, <hi>I AM,</hi> is the Name that ſhall continue and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, and whereby men ſhall be bleſſed, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.6. <hi>For I am the Lord, I change not.</hi> From hence you may ſee the nature of Gods Name to his People, He is the ſame, and changes not, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 135.3. <hi>Thy Name, O Lord, endureth for ever, and thy Memorial, O Lord, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all generations.</hi> From hence you may obſerve the ſweet harmony and joynt-agreement, the Spirit of God hath here with my Text, the ſelf ſame language expreſſed.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, take notice, with what <hi>Zeal</hi> and <hi>Affection,</hi> and <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial deſire,</hi> the Prophet <hi>Declares the Name of the Lord. Oh Lord,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>thy Name endures for ever;</hi> and when he ſpeakeh of Gods <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorial, O Lord,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>it endures to all generations,</hi> he fals as is were into admiration of the Name of God. The next Verſe declares part of Gods Name. Firſt, His Faithfulneſs, <hi>He will judge His People,</hi> or plead for them. Secondly, His Mercy, <hi>And He will repent Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf concerning His ſervants,</hi> and that is in keeping back the intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed evil, and giving them the promiſed good. One text more, and then I have done with this, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 63.15, 16. The People and Church of God at that time, as it is now, were in a very miſerable and deplorable ſtate, as may be diſcerned by their expreſſions in their requeſts: <hi>Look down from Heaven, and behold from the habitation of Thy Holineſs and Glory.</hi> And the Church ſeems to remind the Lord of ſome remiſneſs in ſome things, as if God had been wanting to ſome
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:137005:8"/>of his diſtreſſed People, and ſo had forſaken them, and therefore in vehement ſorrow ſaith, <hi>Where is Thy zeal, Thy ſtrength, the ſounding of Thy bowels and of Thy mercies, are they reſtrained?</hi> As if this poor People ſhould ſay, <hi>Ah Lord, Our Condition is ſad, our State miſerable, and Thou ſeemeſt to be a ſtranger, Where is Thy zeal, Thy affection to Us? How doth that ſeem to decline and decay? Where is Thy ſtrength that ſhould be moſt helpful to us now? Oh where is the ſounding of Thy bowels and mercies, where is that yearning of bowels, that ſympathizing, that compaſſionate, melting, commiſerating of thy Peoples miſeries? Ah Lord,</hi> ſay they, <hi>are they reſtrained, are they bound up, art Thou grown obdurate againſt Thy poor People?</hi> Now do but obſerve what Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments this poor afflicted People uſe, and from thence draws com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Intereſt they had in God; <hi>Donbtleſs,</hi> ſay they, <hi>without all doubt Thou art our Father, though Abraham be ignorant of us, and thou art our Father, though Iſrael acknowledge us not.</hi> From hence you may obſerve three Things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That Saints in the greateſt of miſeries have an eye to the Intereſt they have in God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Intereſt in God is of great ſupport to Saints in times of greateſt ſtraits.</hi> This hath born up the Spirit of Gods People in their trials and ſufferings; what if all the men of the World were mine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and all the malice and envy of men my accuſers, and all the devils my tormentors? yet if God be my Father, if I have an Intereſt in Him, I have all unſpeakable Help, Relief and Support.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The certain aſſured knowledge of the Intereſt in God affords great Comfort, Satisfaction and Contentment to ſuch, though others know it not or be ignorant of it; Though Abraham be ignorant of us,</hi> yet <hi>thou art our Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Second Argument that theſe People ſucked Comfort from, was <hi>the remembrance of Gods Name,</hi> and therefore ſaith, <hi>Thy Name is from Everlaſting;</hi> as if the Church ſhould ſay, though I am afflicted and ſuffer, yet the Name of my God remains, yea it is from ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting. Hence obſerve, <hi>That Gods everlaſting Name afords laſting comfort to his People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third Argument was, <hi>the Relation they had to God,</hi> and that is in the laſt Verſe, <hi>We are Thine,</hi> Thy peculiar People in Covenant with Thee, and Thou never ruleſt over the heathen, Thou never hadſt that rule and reign in their hearts and conſciences, as thou
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:137005:9"/>didſt over and in us, and we are called by Thy Name, we do repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Thee to the World. Thus much ſhall ſuffice for the firſt thing premiſed.</p>
            <p>Now I come to the Second thing propoſed, and that was, <hi>to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare how or wherein Gods Name, I AM, is the ſame to his People in all ages; and that this Truth is of ſuch weight and concernment, that it's able to comfort and conſolate the hearts and ſpirits of Gods People in the midſt of their troubles, and ſufferings:</hi> In the proof of this I ſhall indeavour to ſhew wherein <hi>Gods Name is the ſame to his People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt, as touching Gods Power; His power and ſtrength is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great, that let the troubles be never ſo many, and never ſo great, yet Gods Power is as great yea greater. We will firſt conſult with ſome Scriptures, that ſpeakes aloud to this Truth, and then apply it, <hi>Nahum</hi> 1.3. <hi>The Lord is great in Power;</hi> Oh believe this Truth and it will adminiſter comforts in your Straits; Are your ſufferings great, remember <hi>The Lord is great in Power, Deut.</hi> 9.29. Speaking of the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Thou broughteſt them out by thy migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Power;</hi> as God hath <hi>Mighty Power,</hi> ſo it is ingaged for the good of His People, <hi>Luke</hi> 9.43. <hi>And they were all amazed at the mighty Power of God:</hi> Gods Power is ſo Mighty, that it amazes the very Adverſaries of his People, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.5. <hi>Great is our Lord, and of great Power;</hi> We have a peculiar Relation to Him that hath this great Power, He is our Lord, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1. <hi>I am the Almighty God, walk before me and be thou perfect;</hi> God hath here declared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be the Almighty God, the Alſufficient God, able to anſwer and ſupply all wants and neceſſities, as if God ſhould ſay to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Walk thou before me and be thou perfect.</hi> Now leſt he ſhould object and ſay, <hi>Ah Lord, They that do walk perfectly before thee, will meet with many troubles, be expoſed to many hardſhips and loſſes;</hi> well, ſaith God, matter it not, <hi>I am the Almighty God, the Alſufficient God;</hi> Let the Troubles of his People be never ſo great, yet the Lord is Almighty, great in Power and ſtrength. Now ſeriouſly conſider this firſt thing, as part of the Name of God, remember Gods Name, <hi>I AM,</hi> He is the ſame now as ever he was, as Powerful as ever, as Strong as ever, as Mighty as ever, <hi>This is his Name for Ever, and his Memorial unto all generations.</hi> Oh ſuffering Chriſtians, give me leave to tell you, that your Fathers Power is your greateſt Pillar of ſupport in times of difficulties. See that pretious Text in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:137005:9"/>2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.9. <hi>The eyes of the Lord run to and fro throughout the whole earth,</hi> to ſhew himſelf <hi>ſtrong</hi> in the behalf of thoſe whoſe hearts are perfect towards him. From hence note, <hi>That there is Mighty Power and ſtrength in God, handed forth and exerciſed for the good of his People.</hi> This truth really believed how mightily would it caution the Lords People, to take heed of fears, and to live above them. One word of Uſe, and I conclude this.</p>
            <p>Oh let us ſing Songs of praiſe of our Gods Power, it is true Gods Power is matter of fear and terror to the wicked, but its matter of comfort and joy to the Saints, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 59.16. <hi>I will ſing of thy Power,</hi> when the ſoul is in great troubles, and ſufferings; and conſider what God is, what his Name is, that he is the Mighty Powerful God, and then conſider that he is the ſame, His Name is, <hi>I AM,</hi> that the poor ſoul is ready to ſing forth of Gods Power; Believe it fellow Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, you are in the hand of God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.3. Obſerve all his Saints are in his hand, not ſome but all; oh you be ſafe enough, <hi>there is none can pluck you out of your fathers hand;</hi> and beſides he hath all Power in his hand, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.6. Oh then my dear Brethren, be not hopeleſs, for God leaves you not helpleſs; What can harm you? you have the Power of God to arm you; then labour to undergo all here, for you ſhall not onely be delivered from all, but be conquerors over all. This is the firſt thing.</p>
            <p>A Second thing relating to Gods Name, wherein he is the ſame now as ever, and that is his <hi>Wiſdom;</hi> He is as Wiſe now as ever, and as Prudent in managing his Peoples concernments, as ever. Oh the great Wiſdom of our God, in ordering our affaires, it's matter of great Comfort and Conſolation. But firſt we will ſee what the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſaith concerning Our Gods Wiſdom, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.27. <hi>To God onely Wiſe be glory;</hi> As God is Wiſe, ſo He is <hi>onely Wiſe,</hi> none like Him, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.17. <hi>To the onely Wiſe God be glory.</hi> Col. 2.3. <hi>In whom are hid all the treaſures of VViſdom and Knowledge;</hi> In our God are treaſures of Wiſdom; Conſider this dear friends, is there any Trouble or Calamity befalls you, that you know not how to come out of it, or be rid of it, well remember that your God hath <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of VViſdom and Knowledge.</hi> Iſa. 40.28. <hi>There is no ſearching of the Lords Underſtanding,</hi> it is ſo deep and large, and therefore though that cannot be ſearched, yet it can ſearch all things, God is the alone and onely VViſe God, now in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.25. there is a ſaying ſomething ſtrange, that the Apoſtle ſpeaks, and ſome would
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:137005:10"/>be apt to conclude, that it was ſomething contradictory to what hath been ſaid; his words are, <hi>that the fooliſhneſs of God is wiſer then men;</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timating, as if there were ſome <hi>Fooliſhneſs in God;</hi> the Apoſtle doth not ſpeak nor intend it in the leaſt, but he was ſpeaking of upbraid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mens wiſdom, that to ſuch the <hi>fooliſhneſs of God was wiſer,</hi> he doth not ſay, <hi>the fooliſhneſs in God,</hi> but <hi>of God;</hi> but had allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the Saints, whom as fooliſh things of God, were choſen to confound the Wiſe; Now God is ſo perfect in Wiſdom, that the very Angels he chargeth with folly, and it's ſaid of the Lords Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>it is Infinite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now conſider this ſeriouſly, God is great in Wiſdom, and as he was always ſo he is now, <hi>I AM THAT I AM,</hi> that <hi>is</hi> His <hi>Name for Ever,</hi> a Wiſe God, that by his wiſe diſpoſing of things, can make all things work for good, and can turn all your troubles and ſufferings, to the beſt advantage or profit, that you ſhall reap the fruit thereof with great gain and increaſe; He by His Wiſdom can order the Saints troubles and ſufferings to be further footings to glory and happineſs, that by his Wiſdom can allure His People into the Wilderneſs, and there ſpeak comfortably to them; Now what a comfort is it to conſider, that our Gods Name is <hi>I AM,</hi> ſtill the ſame to His People as ever He was. A word to Apply this, Is our God onely and alone Wiſe, <hi>Then let us leave all our Concernments and affairs to his diſpoſe;</hi> Our Father knows what is beſt for us, and what will conduce to our good and His glory.</p>
            <p>Well, to proceed to the Third thing, and that is <hi>the Faithfulneſs of God;</hi> Gods Faithfulneſs is of mighty weight and concernment, that His Name is, <hi>I AM,</hi> the Faithful God, as Faithful now as ever. Gods Faithfulneſs conſiſts chiefly in fulfilling and perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and making good all Promiſes and Propheſies; See the voice of the Scripture concerning this Truth, <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.8, 9. <hi>But becauſe the Lord God loved you,</hi> here was the Mercy of God, <hi>and becauſe He would keep the Oath which he ſware unto your Fathers,</hi> here was the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of God, <hi>the Lord hath brought you out with a Mighty hand,</hi> here is the Power of God, <hi>and redeemed you from the houſe of bondmen, and out of the hand of Pharaoh king of Egypt,</hi> here is declared the Juſtice of God: Thus conſider, ſee, and obſerve here you have His Name, which he ſent by <hi>Moſes</hi> to his People, <hi>I AM THAT I AM, this is my Name for Ever;</hi> See what the Lord ſaith further in the ninth <hi>Verſe, Know therefore that the Lord thy God He is God,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:137005:10"/>What God? <hi>A Faithful God, which keepeth Covenant and Mercy, with thoſe that love Him and keep His Commandments to a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand generations.</hi> The Lord is not onely exactly, compleatly, and perfectly Faithful, but he is mighty large in his Faithfulneſs, the extent of it reacheth to a <hi>thouſand Generations;</hi> Here the Lord in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes and intends all his People, that are, or ever will be in the VVorld: One Generation continues about a hundred years if not more. Now its not reaſonable to imagine, that there would be from that time theſe words were ſpoken, to the end of the World, a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Generations; Onely this Scripture ſhews the large extent of the Faithfulneſs of God, it reaches all Saints in all Ages, even to a <hi>thouſand Generations,</hi> if it be poſſible there may be ſo many, while the VVorld continues. Oh lay up this Word of God in your hearts, our God is a Faithful God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. <hi>God is Faithful, who will not ſuffer you to be tempted above what you are able, but will with the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation, make a way to eſcape, that ye may be able to bear it:</hi> The faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of God is as much ingaged in his Peoples ſufferings, as any other of His Attributes. In His Peoples Sufferings His Faithfulneſs is engaged Three ways.</p>
            <p>Firſt that their Sufferings ſhall not exceed,
<list>
                  <item>1. His Precepts to them.</item>
                  <item>2. Other Saints before them.</item>
                  <item>3. The ſtrength he gives them.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, His Faithfulneſs is engaged, that in their Sufferings for Him, He will ſtand by them, own them, and be with them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, His Faithfulneſs is ingaged to make good his Promiſes to them, in delivering and freeing them from troubles. Oh Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are your troubles and Sufferings great, and like to be greater, and you are even ready to ſink under them; well remember your Gods Name, <hi>I AM THAT I AM:</hi> He is the Faithful God, as Faithful now as ever, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.5. <hi>Thy Mercy O Lord is in the Heavens, and thy faithfulneſs reacheth to the clouds.</hi> This Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture holds forth the multitude or abundance of Gods Faithfulneſs, <hi>that it reacheth to the clouds;</hi> As wicked mens ſins, when they are multitudes and numerous, they are ſaid <hi>to reach up to Heaven;</hi> ſo the Faithfulneſs of God is ſo continued to his, that it even reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth up to the clouds, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.90. <hi>Thy Faithfulneſs is to all ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations;</hi> This alſo is a precious Scripture, that no ſoul in no age, though in the laſt days, and in the latter end of the World, when wickedneſs will abound, and ſtrange and dark Providences, with
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:137005:11"/>deſmal diſpenſations will be ſeen in the earth, yet Gods faithfulneſs abides ſtill, it endures unto all generations; therefore no ſoul, in what age or ſtate ſoever, ſhould be caſt down or troubled, but to mind the Name of God, <hi>I AM THAT I AM,</hi> the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful God: Oh that Chriſtians in all their troubles and ſufferings would have an eye to the Faithfulneſs of God, and unfeignedly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it, for it's of mighty uſe to bear up your hearts in the midſt of troubles; and truly I am perſwaded, that when God ſent <hi>Moſes</hi> with his Name <hi>I AM,</hi> to his afflicted People, he had thus much in his eye, and upon his heart, His Faithfulneſs in keeping Covenant with them, and performing His Promiſes to them: The Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of God is one of his principal Attributes, and the great ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor and beauty of his Name, though all the Attributes of God are Perfect; What were it (if I may ſpeak with holy reverence) for God to be Powerful and Wiſe, if not Faithful? The Faithfulneſs of God is the great Bulwark of his People in their Troubles. Conſider that in no age, there was no Saint whatſoever to whom God was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithful: If ſome ſay, there may be ſome one or other; ſhew me that man or woman, what is their Name, where dwell they, when was it, or where was it, that God was not Faithful? I dare engage my ſoul, and its eternal welfare, that God is not unfaithful to any of his; Far be it from me, or any to think that there is unfaithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in God; His People may be unfaithful to Him, but He will not be ſo to them; If there be any of Gods Promiſes not perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it's not His fault, but His Peoples; His Promiſes being Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal, they breaking, or not keeping the Condition, and ſo miſs of the Promiſe to which the Condition is annexed; They break their Words and Promiſes with the Lord, but as for God, <hi>Let Him be true, and every man a liar;</hi> nay, it's impoſſible for God to lye. Thus much for the Third thing.</p>
            <p>A Fourth thing concerning Gods Name, is <hi>His Juſtice;</hi> God is very Juſt and Righteous, and that is, in rendering puniſhment on his Enemies.</p>
            <p>Dear Friends, your Enemies are great, and they are many, and their malice, cruelty and oppreſſion, is very much, and increaſed; Well, be not troubled, remember you the Name of your God, <hi>I AM,</hi> He is Juſt, yea and as Juſt now as ever, in puniſhing his enemies; Turn to the Teſtimony, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.16. <hi>The Lord is known by the Judgments which he executeth, the wicked are enſnared in the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:137005:11"/>work of their hands. Higgaion Selah.</hi> This is a Scripture of great weight. There are two ways whereby he is known to the World.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By His Mercies.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By His Judgements: And they that will not know Him the former way ſhall know him the latter. But what ſhall the wicked know of God by his Judgements, that he is a Juſt God, a Righteous God, and ſaith the Spirit of God, <hi>The wicked are enſnared in the work of their own hands.</hi> This is a certain and aſſured truth, That wicked mens handy-works, or their actions, prove their own enſnaring; This was true in <hi>Ahithophel, Haman,</hi> and <hi>Judas,</hi> and therefore the Lord writes upon this Scripture, <hi>Higgaion Selah,</hi> that is, to be often <hi>Obſerving,</hi> and diligently <hi>Meditating</hi> on it, to ſee the Juſtice and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of God to the wicked, in that their own works ſhould enſnare them: <hi>Job</hi> 34.17. God is called there, moſt Juſt, exactly and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly Juſt; as God is faithful in rewarding His People, ſo he is as faithful and Juſt in puniſhing the Wicked. I will make a little Uſe of this, and ſo haſten.</p>
            <p>Fret not your ſelves at the Proſperity and welfare of the wicked, your enemies, neither do you ſeek after revenging your cauſe on them, commit that to the Lord; Vengeance is His, and he is both Mighty and Able to deal with your adverſaries, and He will do it in His due time; <hi>For He will plead the controverſies of His People, againſt their enemies.</hi> And believe it, the Lord is <hi>cutting ſhort the work,</hi> and haſtening the ruine and deſtruction of his enemies, by their filling up the meaſure of their iniquities, and ripening their ſins; and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance of His People draweth nigh, by his caſting them into the Furnace of Affliction, to purge and purifie them, that they may come forth like Gold. Again,</p>
            <p>The Fifth and laſt thing relating to the Name of God, <hi>I AM.</hi> He is the God of all comforts and conſolation; Oh this Name, <hi>I AM,</hi> is a precious Name, there is exceeding great Comforts and Cordials in God for the refreſhing of his poor Peoples Spirits, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Bleſſed the God, the God of our Lord Jeſus, the Father of Mercies, and God of all Comforts.</hi> There is in our God ſuch a Store<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe and Fountain of Mercies and Comforts, that is able to ſupply all His Peoples wants and neceſſities, <hi>Zechariah</hi> 1.17. <hi>The Lord ſhall yet Comfort Zion.</hi> Notwithſtanding the great diſcouragements and diſtreſſes of Gods People, yet Comforts God hath in ſtore for poor bleeding and languiſhing <hi>Sion,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.6. <hi>Nevertheleſs, God
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:137005:12"/>that Comforteth thoſe that are caſt down, Comforteth us.</hi> Oh the choice Comforts that God hath for his dejected People! Though God hath in all ages, been open handed and hearted in the diſpenſing of his Comforts to his People, yet He is as full, and as rich now as ever, His Name is <hi>I AM, this is His Name for Ever,</hi> God hath choice and variety of Comforts, which he communicates, as he ſees moſt neceſſary; I hope by this time, that God hath taught his People by experience, that there is no comfort in outward injoyments, crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures nor relations, but onely in their Lord God, that they may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light themſelves in His Comforts, and not in borrowed, feigned, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing Comforts. Hence ſee, There is no reaſon why Saints ſhould be ſorrowful or caſt down, <hi>there is bread enough in their Fathers houſe,</hi> He is <hi>the God of all Comforts,</hi> His Name is, <hi>I AM.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A little to Apply this, and ſo proceed.</p>
            <p>Hence ſee your Priviledges, Excellency and Prerogative, that this God that I have been treating of, whoſe Name is <hi>I AM,</hi> is your God, poor ſuffering <hi>Sions</hi> God; Oh <hi>Sion,</hi> though now miſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, yet thy condition, thy ſtate, ſo good, ſo glorious, that the ſtate of Potentates is not fit to be compared with it; thy bonds and iron chains, are of far greater value than Crowns &amp; Diadems; there is not a ſtep of Miſery or Suffering, that doth befal <hi>Sion</hi> upon <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah's</hi> account, but it conduces a footſtep to its further happineſs and glory: And all this, becauſe this God, whoſe Name is <hi>I AM,</hi> is theirs; though <hi>Sions</hi> foes which are many and mighty may bereave her of all comfortable things here, yet this God of Comforts they cannot take away.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Take heed my Brethren and fellow Citizens of Glory, of ſinning and offending ſuch, ſuch a God as this is, be careful of grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of Him, leſt He withdraw himſelf, and hide his face from you; Oh remember and fear that ſad Lamentation, in <hi>Lamentation</hi> 1.16. This Church of God had very much ſinned againſt the God of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts; See <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. <hi>Jeruſalem hath grievouſly ſinned:</hi> but ſee the ſad complaint ſhe makes, <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. <hi>For theſe things I weep, mine eye, mine eye runneth down with water:</hi> Why what was the matter, that this Church doth ſo ſorrow and lament? Mark, <hi>becauſe the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter that ſhould relieve my ſoul, is far from me:</hi> Oh let their fals be your warnings.</p>
            <p>But Thirdly conſider, if God be ſo to his People now, as I have declared, and continues his Name <hi>I AM</hi> to them in an afflicted
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:137005:12"/>ſtate, ſuffering ſtate, low and miſerable ſtate; Oh do but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider and that with aſtoniſhment, what will he do for them, and be to them, when they are in a glorified ſtate, perfected ſtate? Doth he do thus to them now they are uncomely, now they wear raggs, now they are the off-ſcouring, now they have their imperfections, and failings towards Him? Oh, oh, what will his Name, <hi>I AM,</hi> be to them then, when they ſhall be very comely, when they ſhall ſhine as the Sun, be equal with Angels, full of holineſs and perfection? Conſider this and ſtand in admiration.</p>
            <p>If God afords a mighty preſence to <hi>a burning Buſh,</hi> to a <hi>ſuffering creature,</hi> oh what will he do to <hi>a glorified Saint!</hi> Thus much for the Second thing.</p>
            <p>Now the Third thing propoſed was, <hi>The Reaſons and Grounds why the Lord continues his Name, I AM, the ſame to his People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>That they might not be deſtroyed nor conſumed.</hi> Gods un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changableneſs to us, is the cauſe of our not changing from our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to worſe. See <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.6. <hi>I am the Lord, I change not; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ye ſons of Jacob are not conſumed;</hi> as if the Lord ſhould ſay, <hi>I am the Lord, I AM THAT I AM, this is my Name for Ever, I change not; for this cauſe my People are not conſumed.</hi> Ah my friends, if God were changable as man, and as mutable as man, where ſhould we have been at this time? how ſoon would our condition be far worſe then it is? Really, if God ſhould not continue his Name to his People, <hi>I AM,</hi> His <hi>Power,</hi> His <hi>Faithfulneſs,</hi> His <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> His <hi>Comforts,</hi> their ſtate would be very miſerable.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, <hi>Why this Name of God is continued for ever to his People?</hi> It is to engage them to Him, to draw up the hearts and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of His People cloſe to Him: If any Truth is of an ingaging nature, this is; it engages the Saints in their whole man for God, their life and all for God, yea and that in the worſt of times; If the very Name of God be engaged for me, there is all the Reaſon, why my All ſhould be engaged for God. And therefore Chriſtians look to it, that wherein you come ſhort in this particular, you come ſhort in anſwering the end of Gods Name to you. I muſt but name the Reaſons of this Truth, becauſe of time.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, to ſhew, <hi>Why God continues his Name for Ever;</hi> becauſe that there is none like him, nor none to be compared to him; he is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:137005:13"/>indeed <hi>the chiefeſt of ten thouſand:</hi> there is no King like Him, nor no Potentate like Him, a man may be in their favours to day, and, at a little diſpleaſing of them, be turned out to morrow; but its not ſo with our God, whoſe Name is, <hi>I AM,</hi> its not a ſmall matter that moves Him to take hold of Judgement: He is ſaid to be <hi>ſlow to anger,</hi> though its true, a ſmall matter (moves Him to Mercy) and when His People do ſin againſt him, yet he is loath to uſe the rod, if Mercy may prevaile, yea He <hi>waits to be gratious;</hi> there is no Fathers, nor Husbands like to our God, for they are momentary and periſh, but our God <hi>endures,</hi> and his <hi>Name to all Generations.</hi> This being ſeriouſly conſidered, is it not reaſonable to leave and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake all to cleave to this God: What have we to do, to own or ſtand by any earthly Monarch, but onely that <hi>Monarch</hi> KING JESUS, Who in Scripture is declared to be, <hi>The onely Potentate,</hi> and all near and dear Relations are to be forſaken, when they come in competition with our God.</p>
            <p>But Fourthly, Becauſe of the near Relation between God and his People, He therefore continues his Name to them; God is rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his People, not onely as a <hi>Father,</hi> and they <hi>his Children,</hi> but He as their <hi>Bridegroom</hi> and <hi>Huſband,</hi> and they <hi>His Wife</hi> and <hi>Spouſe;</hi> and ſo from that near Relation to them, he reſerves entire affection for them.</p>
            <p>But Fifthly, <hi>Why God continues his Name for Ever to his People;</hi> Becauſe of the great need and neceſſity His People ſtand in of him: whilſt His People are here, they are ſubject to wants and neceſſities, both to the outward and inward man, and therefore the Lord con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues his Name.</p>
            <p>But Laſtly, Becauſe of the ſweet Promiſes of the Lord, to his People. See the 28. <hi>Matth.</hi> 18, 20. <hi>All Power in Heaven and Earth is mine, and lo I am with you to the end of the World,</hi> This <hi>I AM</hi> hath promiſed <hi>to be with them to the end of the World,</hi> and therefore <hi>continues his Name to them for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I ſhall come to the laſt thing I propoſed, and that was, <hi>The wholſome Uſes and Concluſions of this Truth;</hi> which are ten.</p>
            <p>Firſt is, Gods Name, <hi>I AM.</hi> Is He the <hi>ſame</hi> to his People now that <hi>Ever</hi> He was, doth he not change? <hi>Then let His People be exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the fear of the Lord to be alwayes the ſame to the Lord, as they have profeſſed, and not change in their love, and ſervice to Him.</hi> Oh my
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:137005:13"/>friends, this that I ſpeak <hi>is but your reaſonable ſervice.</hi> God is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changable to you, be you ſo to him, though not in the quantity of it, yet in the quality of it; the Lord is as Powerful for you now as Ever, Oh be you ſo to Him, lay out all your ſtrength and might for him; the Lord is as Wiſe now to order things for your good as ever, be you therefore Wiſe for Him, let your care and prudence be to pleaſe Him, and your wiſdom to walk ſo, that he may be honoured; the Lord is as Faithful for you now as ever, be you therefore Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for Him, and manifeſt your Faithfulneſs;</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. In a due obſervance of all his known Commands.</item>
               <item>2. In a circumſpect Walking before Him.</item>
               <item>3. In a faithful Teſtimony againſt the Abomination of the Day.</item>
               <item>4. In a cloſe and full Following of the Lord, through all Trials and Sufferings.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Conſider that precious Scripture, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.32. <hi>But call to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance the former days, in which after ye were illuminated, ye endured a great fight of Afflictions;</hi> How ſeaſonable might this word of Alarm be given to the Churches of Chriſt in theſe Iſles? how are they dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated? how have they declined, and turned their backs upon the great and holy Commands of God, that at the Command of a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal man, omit, and lay aſide the Worſhip and Service of God? It's my earneſt deſire, that the Lord would rouſe and waken his poor ſhattered and decayed Churches, <hi>that they may remember from whence they are fallen and repent, and remember their former days,</hi> the days of Liberty and freedom, wherein they were very zealous and couragious for God, and made ſolemn Promiſes and Engagements, what they would do, and be for God, in an evil day: Let all the Lords People ſeriouſly conſider and examine. Oh be exhorted to be as zealous for God now as ever, be as faithful for Him now as ever, ſeeing Gods <hi>Name is the ſame</hi> now as <hi>Ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Second Concluſion of this point is; Is Gods Name <hi>I AM,</hi> the ſame to his People as ever? Then <hi>This Doctrine ſpeakes terror to the wicked, Gods enemies;</hi> and that upon two accounts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This God is none of theirs, they have no Intereſt in His Name, and all that I have ſpoken, they are not at all concerned in it; its true <hi>Gods Name is pretious,</hi> but its onely to his People, the dearly beloved of his Soul.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This ſpeaks terror to the wicked, in that, as God is not theirs, ſo he is their enemy, their foe, His <hi>Power,</hi> His <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> His <hi>Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs,</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:137005:14"/>His Juſtice, is all engaged againſt them; God is not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come their enemy upon the account of the firſt mans tranſgreſſions, for all that is pardoned, juſtified, and acquitted, and reconciled. God ſtands an enemy to men now, by reaſon of their actual ſins, their rebellion againſt God, oppoſing his ways, hating his People.</p>
            <p>A Third Concluſion of this truth is; Is Gods Name <hi>I AM?</hi> Is He the ſame to his People now as ever, and that for ever? <hi>Then let this teach us to live by faith, to look now on inviſibles, to live no more by ſence, but to act faith in a high meaſure; for Gods Name is I AM,</hi> Rom. 1.28.</p>
            <p>There are Three principal Things in living by Faith.</p>
            <p n="1">1. You anſwer the work of the day; the very work of this day calls loudly to Saints for a <hi>living by Faith;</hi> the very dealings and diſpenſations of God, intend no leſs then a <hi>living by Faith:</hi> Did ever poor <hi>Sion</hi> ſee ſuch a day as this? They who are awakned, and right ſenſible, know my meaning; It's not for you Chriſtians now to live by ſence, but to look up higher.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Your <hi>living by Faith,</hi> makes you more ſingular and peculiar in your life than others; this will eminently diſtinguiſh the <hi>ſincere</hi> from the <hi>hypocrite,</hi> the <hi>precious</hi> from the <hi>vile:</hi> If the carnal and lukewarm profeſſor live by ſence, let not the Spiritual Chriſtian do ſo; Oh you muſt live more ſingular than others, for to you this Name of God, <hi>I AM,</hi> is for ever.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Living by Faith</hi> frees you from fears; I never wonder that men are ſo full of fears, they live ſo much by ſence, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7. <hi>We walk by Faith and not by ſight;</hi> It's the living too much upon ſight and ſence that produceth fears, but the living by Faith, doth prevent fears and doubts. See 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.16. The Apoſtle is declaring there, that notwithſtanding all their troubles and trials, yet they fainted not, they were not poſſeſſed with fears; And what was the reaſon of it? pray ſee <hi>verſ.</hi> 18. <hi>While we look not at the things which are ſeen, but at the things which are not ſeen; for the things that are ſeen are temporal, but the things which are not ſeen are eternal.</hi> Hence ſee the reaſon and ground, why theſe pretious ſouls did not fear nor faint in their trials, they <hi>lived by Faith</hi> and not <hi>by ſence;</hi> and this is a great cauſe and ground of fears and doubts this day, in the hearts of many of the Lords People; They look upon ſeen things, things that are; they ſee and behold great men are againſt them, the Nobles, the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, the Mayors, the Army is againſt them; they look and ſee
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:137005:14"/>themſelves all weak and impotent, moſt of them in ſtrong Priſons; I but this was not the Primitive Saints practice, for they did <hi>look not at things ſeen,</hi> for ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>they are temporal,</hi> all periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Kings are temporal, Generals, Mayors, and Armies are temporal and periſhing; Well, ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>We look at things which are not ſeen,</hi> and that looking was by Faith, and <hi>the things not ſeen,</hi> were <hi>the great King of kings, the Lord of hoſts, all the powerful and mighty Angels,</hi> and the like; And this was Eternal, God Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, His Name Eternal, his Power and Faithfulneſs Eternal.</p>
            <p>A Fourth Concluſion from theſe Words is, Seeing Gods Name is <hi>I AM,</hi> the ſame that ever he was to his People; Then <hi>Take heed of caſting dirt on the Name of God, be careful of villifying of it;</hi> It's very ſad to conſider that many profeſſing themſelves Children of God, ſhould be inſtrumental to help the blaſpheming of Gods Name; Oh that this precious Name ſhould be blemiſhed by any of His People! <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.24. <hi>For the Name of God is blaſphemed among the Gentiles, through you;</hi> They were the cauſe. How tender are men of their own Name and Reputation? how much more then ſhould they be of Gods? Oh me thinks how ſad is it to conſider, that the wicked daily reproach Gods Name, and villifie it, and yet for his own Children to add and help to it? <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.7. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle calls it, <hi>A worthy Name, which men blaſpheme:</hi> And believe it, of all things, God takes it moſt heinouſly from his People; He ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects little elſe from his Enemies, but far better from his People: To receive a wound from a dear friend, pierces inward. And one thing you may obſerve by the way, <hi>That God deales more ſpeedily and ſeverely with his People, for occaſioning his Names blaſpheming, than with the wicked:</hi> Witneſs <hi>David</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>A Fifth Concluſion of this Point; Seeing Gods Name is <hi>I AM,</hi> the ſame to his People for Ever: Then <hi>Endeavour to hold faſt the Name of God;</hi> Let there be a cloſe keeping of it, not onely hold it, but hold it faſt: See <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.13. The great Praiſe and Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of this People was, in that <hi>They held faſt the Name of God, and did not deny his Faith;</hi> but their greater glory, and excellency was, <hi>They held faſt his Name in bad times,</hi> and <hi>bad places; Thou dwelleſt,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>where Satan dwelleth, where Satans ſeat is,</hi> and there, yea in that place, <hi>thou heldeſt faſt my Name;</hi> And beſides, <hi>thou heldeſt faſt my Name in a very bad time, even in thoſe days wherein Antipas My faithful Martyr was ſlain:</hi> It was a great day of trial and trouble,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:137005:15"/>a day of much Perſecution, yet in ſuch a day as this did theſe ſouls <hi>hold faſt the Name of God.</hi> And concerning <hi>Antipas,</hi> you have Two things remarkable from the Lords mouth:</p>
            <p>Firſt, that of all his virtues and graces, which were many, God commends and takes notice chiefly of his Faithfulneſs; <hi>Antipas my Faithful ſervant:</hi> Oh God chiefly eyes, principally minds, and eminently will reward His Peoples Faithfulneſs towards Him. <hi>Antipas</hi> being a great Pillar in the Church, abounds in many vertues, his love to God, to his People, to the ſouls of men; his Faith, Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Prayer and Sincerity; Oh but Perſeverance crowns all; it's Faithfulneſs that Gods heart is much affected with.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, The Lord calls <hi>Antipas his faithful Martyr, My Martyr;</hi> though it's poſſible he died as an Evil-doer, as an Heretick, and Blaſphemous Hereſie; It's no matter, how men put him to death, how men called him, God owns and calls him, <hi>His Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr.</hi> This ſhould encourage Saints, not to matter how ignomini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and ſhamefully they ſuffer, ſtigmatized with dreadful Names, yet God ſpeaks otherwiſe, <hi>His thoughts are not as mens thoughts.</hi> Now in Three Things the Lords People may be ſaid to <hi>hold faſt His Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. By a holy and reverend eſteem thereof, there ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence to it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By a heavenly and ſpecial walking ſutable to it, to the honour and praiſe thereof.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By not counting any thing dear to it, our own Names and Lives meet to be given up for it.</p>
            <p>A Sixth Concluſion of this Subject is; Is Gods Name, <hi>I AM,</hi> to his People the ſame for Ever? <hi>Oh then Praiſe and Prize this God, let your hearts be drawn forth in Praiſing of Him;</hi> Here is matter and ground of Praiſe for His People to all generations, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.4. <hi>Sing unto God, ſing Praiſes to his Name.</hi> And Pſal. 96.8. <hi>Give unto the Lord the glory due to his Name:</hi> Praiſes are due to the Name of God, Oh therefore Praiſe this Name of God: And that upon a Fourfold account.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He is yours peculiarly, you have a peculiar Intereſt and right to him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He is yours freely, the Intereſt you have in him, came freely to you, though dear to Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He is wholly yours, you have a whole God, and a whole Chriſt,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:137005:15"/>nor a part: Every particular and individual Saint in the World can ſay properly and truly, I have a God, I have a Father.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He is Eternally yours; Oh this is the chiefeſt of all, and therefore Prize the Lord.</p>
            <p>A Seventh Concluſion from this Truth, that ſeeing Gods Name is <hi>I AM,</hi> the ſame now as ever; <hi>Be perſwaded then to ſuffer and dye for His Name.</hi> I am verily perſwaded, that had we a right ſence and feeling of this Name of God to us, we ſhould be mightily drawn forth, with the Apoſtle Paul, <hi>not onely to ſuffer bonds, but to die for His Name;</hi> And truly God is not wanting, but will do great things for thoſe that Suffer for his Name: See <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.132. <hi>David</hi> Beggs, <hi>That the Lord would do for him, as He uſed to do for thoſe that loved his Name;</hi> Implying, the Lord did wonderfully for them; And what greater love can be manifeſted to Gods Name, than ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering or dying for it?</p>
            <p>The Eight Concluſion from this Point, is God's Name <hi>I AM:</hi> Is he the ſame to his People now as ever? Then let this ſerve to quiet, ſtill and ſatisfie the Spirits of God's People in the midſt of Troubles, of the Lords Diſpenſation, and of the Worlds Deſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Oh this Precious Cordial, <hi>I AM!</hi> the ſame God, rightly believed and rightly applied, is able to make a Calm in the greateſt Storm, to afford Peace in the midſt of Trouble; it's the true Balm for every diſquieted and dejected Mind. See that precious Text, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46.10. ſpeaking before of great Troubles in the World, great Deſtractions, and ſtrange Diſpenſations, he comes in the 10. verſ. and ſpeaks to the People of God: <hi>Be ſtill,</hi> do not you be troubled, be not you caſt down nor diſquieted, <hi>but know that I am God:</hi> What God? a powerful God, a wiſe God, a faithful God, the God of Comforts; <hi>I AM THAT I AM; This is my Name for Ever, and my Memorial unto all Generations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Ninth Concluſion I draw from this Truth: That ſeeing Gods Name is <hi>I AM,</hi> the ſame that ever He was; Then let your ſpiritual Wiſdom be improved, in turning <hi>bad Sights</hi> into <hi>good Signs:</hi> Do you ſee dark and diſmal Sights? Oh remember God's Name, and make good Signs of them: Do you ſee the Sun ſtand ſtill? Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member it was for the Deliverance of God's People by the hand of <hi>Joſhua?</hi> Doth the Dyal of <hi>Ahaz</hi> go backward fifteen degrees? Oh remember it was a Sign to adde fifteen Years to the life of good <hi>Hezekiah.</hi> Oh improve God's Diſpenſations by acting Faith in the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:137005:16"/>Remembrance of his Name; and all ſad Sights that may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to your view, be as Tokens of future good Signs. <hi>Luke</hi> 21.28. <hi>When theſe things come to paſſe,</hi> (the verſes before-going, ſhew what things they were) Well, what muſt we do when they come to paſſe? <hi>then do you look up, and lift up your heads; for your Redemption draweth nigh.</hi> The worſt of Diſpenſations affords matter of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation for Gods People; and the Reaſon lyes here, their God is <hi>I AM.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Tenth and laſt Concluſion of this Subject: Let all the Sons and Daughters of <hi>Sion</hi> be intreated to let this Truth, briefly touched upon, dwell in their ſouls, and ſink deep in your hearts and minds, when you are compaſſed about with greater Troubles, with greater Fears, with greater Tryals and Sufferings than now you have: Oh fix your heart and eye upon this Truth; know that the Lord is God, His Name is <hi>I AM; That is His Name for Ever, and His Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial to all Generations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To Conclude, Lay up in your hearts theſe Scriptures, <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 20.7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 124.8. And the Lord give you underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and bleſſing in theſe things.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:137005:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
